All right, here we go.
Uh
So, I'm going to follow the homework
master. Aren't you happy?
But, probably I'll get distracted and
talk too long.
And maybe won't even finish the first
class, but let's try, okay? So, here we
go.
Uh
I called uh the first course. And And
the fun thing about this teacher
training is that uh I'm going to share
with you some of
what was happening, why I wrote the
courses. You see what I mean?
Like, what was happening or what I was
thinking about. So, uh
if I can remember. Uh so, the first
course is called the principal teachings
of Buddhism. But, the real book
uh that I translated is called Lam Rim
Nam Sum. Say Lam.
Lam.
Rim.
Nam.
Sum.
Which is short for Lam Rim Nam Sum,
okay?
And uh
Okay, I was teaching Marsha a new word
yesterday. Where are you? She's
disappearing.
Oh, sorry.
The pet peeve
Mhm? What's it mean?
Did she get it right, Joel? My pet
peeve.
No.
I taught her American idiom yesterday.
I'm I'm American idiom teacher for a lot
of my students. Pet peeve means uh
the one thing that irritates me a lot,
okay?
And uh it's people who misspell
principal teachings of Buddhism.
So, if you want to fail your teacher
training course,
just spell it wrong.
Okay? So, let's talk about it.
Principal, p a l,
means main, main teachings, okay? And
it's an adjective,
normally,
except for the principal of a school,
which is a man or woman who's the boss
of the school, okay? But principal
teachings, you're going to spell it with
p a l,
which means main teaching, okay?
What's principal mean with a p l e?
It means an important idea, okay? Like
the principle of gravity
or the principle of relativity, okay? So
get it straight, okay? Don't embarrass
me in front of your students.
I've seen many teachers do that.
Okay? We're talking principal teachings,
p a l, okay?
Some people have mistranslated it as
the three principles, p l e,
but that's cuz they don't understand
that the Tibetan word so
has to come after what it modifies,
which is extremely rare.
Okay? So lam ki to means it doesn't mean
the principles of the path.
It doesn't mean that, and many people
have translated that way.
So you can just throw the book out if
you see that at the top.
And you don't know how many books I've
thrown out that way.
It's
So the unfortunately, the word so, which
means
main, primary, principal, p a l,
always comes after the noun that it
modifies, okay? Like book of red,
rather than red book, okay? Got it?
Just nod.
Sometimes the adjective comes after the
noun. This is a dress of red. You see
what I mean?
Meaning red dress, okay?
Anyway,
people got confused.
And it it's a pet peeve. It irritates
me, okay? So you're not going to do
that.
Okay.
Uh
So three main paths, path,
paths of Buddhism is the real title.
Okay? I changed it to the principal
teachings of Buddhism to make it easier.
More
accessible. Okay? More accessible.
And the book, the translated book
with Tsongkhapa on the front
uh
is called The Principal Teachings of
Buddhism. It's not called The Three
Principal Paths. Okay?
And it was meant to be make it more
accessible. By the way, that painting or
that statue
on the front of that book, which is
probably in the
bookstore, I don't know.
Uh
that's a real image of Tsongkhapa. Okay?
It's the only one.
So, uh it was a real statue
of Jetsun Tsongkhapa and it's got big
nose and big ears.
And that's the way he was. Okay? His
enemies called him Mr. Big Nose.
And he had a very big nose. Okay? He He
was face was very strong. Okay? Fuerte.
Okay? And uh
that's a real picture. That statue was
destroyed uh during the Cultural
Revolution. And uh they put another one
They made another one that's all pretty
and handsome and
that's not the real one. Okay? So,
that's why it's black and white.
Cuz the photograph was taken in the in
in the late 1940s or something like
that. Okay?
All right.
Uh so, you first course is based on
The Principal Teachings of Buddhism,
which is more correctly called
The Three Principal Paths of Buddhism.
Three Principal Path. Now, path
lam in Tibetan. What is it in Sanskrit?
Marga.
In this case, doesn't mean
a a road.
And it doesn't mean uh
a method.
It doesn't mean that. In
the Prajnaparamita teachings, okay?
Topic number four.
Path is a synonym for understanding or
realization, okay? It means a mental
state, okay? So, we're not talking about
three methods of Buddhism.
We're not even talking about three ways
that you can go in Buddhism. We're
talking about three attitudes, okay? Got
it? And that's very important. If you
don't understand that, you don't
understand the course, okay?
We're not talking about three methods.
We're not talking about three routes
along a highway. We're talking about
three attitudes
that are the principal teachings of
Buddhism. Got it?
So, we're not talking about books. We're
talking about ideas. Three big ideas,
okay?
And that's something you should know.
The author is
Jetsun Kapa, okay? Sorry.
Uh
Je means, by the way, lord. It's a honor
honorable name like Laozu
La- Laozu.
But Laozu is like elder teacher, right?
It's only Like it's like that. It's
It's Je. Je means uh
For example, diamond
is called in Tibetan
Dorje, which means king of stones.
Do means stone.
Je means lord.
So, Je Tsongkhapa means lord Tsongkhapa.
It's respect word, okay? So,
you can call him uh Tsongkhapa, but it's
a little bit impolite.
And if you call him Je Tsongkhapa, it's
more polite, okay?
Sometimes we call him Je Rinpoche, which
means precious lord. Rinpoche means like
you're like a jewel, okay?
So, if they say Je Rinpoche, they're
talking about Tsongkhapa, okay?
So, you can use either one. It's kind of
weird to say Tsongkhapa.
Then a lot of people spell his name with
a k h.
It's on cap.
Cap like many many people.
That's a pet peeve of mine.
Okay, they are confusing
uh the transliteration
with the sound, okay? When you take a
foreign word
and you put it in English,
you put the sound.
You don't try to capture the spelling in
the in the original language, okay? Got
it? Otherwise, you end up with things
like Sri Lanka
or Sivananda Yoga Center,
which is both mistaken. They're both
mistaken. They are failed transcription.
They are not the sound. Got it?
It's a weird mistake. If you see a book
that have Sounkapa on and on the front,
just throw it out.
It means the person who wrote it doesn't
understand the difference
between transcription and pronunciation.
Got it? What's the transcription for
Moscow?
m o s k v a
m o s k v a is the transcription. Got
it? We pronounce it
Moscow, okay? So, got it?
Don't put the
spelling of the foreign language, put
the sound, okay? Got it?
Sounkapa, just k. There's no reason to
put k h. They messed up my lama's name
at the passport agency.
He's Tarchin.
Okay? Cuz they saw the t the t h in the
transcription.
Got it?
It's so terrible to ruin someone's name
uh cuz you can't tell the difference
between the
the character and the sound. Understand?
Okay?
You're never going to do that
or I will get irritated, more irritated.
Now, his monk's name
This is all I'm just working from the
homeworks.
Uh is say Lobsang.
Trakpa.
Lobsang.
Lobsang means pure mind. Okay, lo means
mind and sang means pure and b is a
prefix letter. So, Lobsang, okay?
Pure-minded one.
Uh Sumati in uh
in Sanskrit. Okay? And uh his last name
is Trakpa, which is what in
Sanskrit.
Kirti. Like Dharmakirti, Chandrakirti.
Kirti means famous. Everyone heard of
this guy. He's amazing, okay? Super
popular.
Okay? So, his name is pure-minded super
Okay? That's his monk's name.
Now, in the rules of monk's names, you
take your
you take the first name of the person
who made you a monk, okay?
Like the normal abbot period
in Sera Mey Monastery for
600 years
is 4 years.
So, during those 4 years, if the abbot's
name is Mike,
then every monk who's made that 4 years,
their first name is Mike.
And we had a big problem at our Sera Mey
because the abbot stayed for three
terms,
12 years.
Half the monks in the monastery are
called Jampa.
And it's really confusing, okay? The you
So, my first name monk name is Lobsang.
And ultimately, I come from Tsongkhapa.
You see, my teacher teacher teacher
teacher teacher. Got it? Okay.
All right. Mmm.
Number two.
What's the actual name of this work,
Three Principal Paths? Okay, you know
that. It's not the It's not the
principal teachings of Buddhism, but
it's the same p a p a l, okay?
All right. Question three, we're working
through homework number one. Yay.
Uh
now,
in in Christian tradition, there's a big
uh emphasis on epistles.
What's an epistle?
It's like a
a heavy letter, like a a letter that
became a classic, you know?
The letters of Paul, right? The epistles
of Paul, which caused a lot of trouble.
He wasn't even there.
Okay.
Uh anyway, epistle means uh sacred
letter, important letter. Okay, so this
book,
the 14 verses, is a letter
that was written to Tsongkhapa's student
named Ngawang Drakpa, okay? Ngawang
Drakpa. You're supposed to know that.
Okay. And you can read it in the
reading. Now,
Ngawang Drakpa had a crush on Tsongkhapa
from the beginning. There's many
paintings of Ngawang Drakpa sitting at
his feet.
So, what did Tsongkhapa do?
You go to East Tibet and build 108
monasteries, you know? And he's like,
"What?"
So,
but he wasn't one of those lazy
disciples.
He did what his teacher told him to do,
even though he didn't want to go. That's
the last thing he wanted to do
was leave his teacher's side.
But Tsongkhapa said, "Go.
And don't come back until you got 108
monasteries, okay?"
And he did it. He went to East Tibet.
He built 108 monasteries. Guess what's
the name of the last one?
Uh-uh. That's Hang.
That's Hang. Uh-uh. That means now.
Hang means I reached the full number,
complete.
Huh. Total.
The last monastery was called Total.
Got it?
I made the total.
Got tongue. And it's a famous monastery.
I used to know the abbot, okay? It's a
cool It's a good monastery. It's still
running, okay?
So, this book was written as a letter to
his student who was upset because he got
told to go out to East Tibet. Okay? And
he's trying to like
what do you call it?
Soften him up a little bit. Yeah, don't
get irritated with me.
You know, here I'll give you a nice
summary of all of Buddhism
in two pages. He's like, "Yeah, okay,
that's cool."
Uh by the way, for $50
Okay, I'm not saying you're interested
in money and not Dharma.
I'm just saying it makes it more fun for
me, okay? I Frankly, it's more fun for
me.
Ready?
In the ACI 18 Foundation courses,
there's another important letter sent to
Ngawang Drakpa.
No.
Why? What's the letter say?
Uh
Yeah, Ngawang Drakpa made the first
monks in East Tibet. And he wrote a
letter to his teacher and said, "Look, I
only not only built monastery, I
ordained a bunch of monks." And
this is the answer by Tsongkhapa.
Don't thumb. Yeah, you want money you
don't want money, honey.
Okay, he forgot. I said the money.
Cancel that one, chopping.
Okay?
You just lost 25 bucks.
Okay,
uh
He told his student, "Do you guys
remember?" Come on.
Yeah, you want to meditate?
It's not the seat. It's not the legs.
It's not the face. It's not the
breathing. It's not the topic. It's
Yeah. Did you respect other people's
peace of mind last week?
Or did you irritate other people?
And the letter is is incredible, you
know? And by the way, in DCI
we we teach them, you know, level
three, we teach them meditation for like
hours after hours. Then at the end we
say, "It doesn't matter."
Nothing matters. What you hear in your
mind
is coming from how you treated people
last week. Don't worry your left foot
goes up first, your right foot goes up
first, you know, can you slouch, can you
not slouch, do you exhale long enough or
not? Forget all this stuff, okay? If you
want to have a good meditation,
don't upset other people's mind.
Okay? Be conscious
to not upset other people's mind. Speak
kindly to people, speak uh with careful
consideration to how they feel. Watch
their face. If they go like that,
then
back off
cuz you're planting seeds to hear crap
in your mind while you meditate.
Okay? You're planting seeds for your
mind to go, "Yeah, what's for lunch?
What's for lunch?"
Okay? That comes from irritating other
people like teaching them tongue and
stuff like that.
I'm just kidding.
Uh okay. He has a nickname, okay?
Say Tsakho.
Tsakho.
Umbo.
By the way, here the uh
the master is mistaken, okay? The old
master from 27 years ago.
It's misspelled. His name is misspelled,
okay? Uh it's Wumbo.
And uh Tsakho is an area that he came
from like uh
like Kansas or Shujo or something, okay?
Like it's a
some Dalian.
Some far away place, okay? Wombo means
uh
It means like a friendly word for local
priest, local
you know? Like the little local priest,
Sakya Wombo, okay? Little local priest
from Sakya.
Okay, so sometimes you might see his
name spelled Sakya, okay? Wombo, okay.
All right.
I didn't put his dates. Guess what? He
lived in the same time as Tsongkhapa.
All right.
Uh
I'm I
I also try to leave out stuff that is
going to overload you, okay? I mean, I
could
put more and more stuff, and we you
would never finish the course, okay?
It'd be like the alarm ringing. Okay.
Uh the commentary you're studying was
written by
Pabongka Rinpoche, and the whole
translation is the course, okay? The
whole translation is in the course. The
whole
the whole commentary is in the course,
okay? Got it?
I trans- I remember where I translated
it. I was on a
1-month retreat
in uh near the Grand Canyon.
Uh and uh
I reme- I remember I translated it
there, okay? Mhm.
Dates of Pabongka Rinpoche:
1878 to 1941.
Uh now,
he was probably
the most famous teacher of the
Tsongkhapa tradition
for that 100 years, okay? He was number
one, okay? So, I'll tell you a little
bit about his story.
Uh and you can read it in the book,
okay? So, in the book,
I got my teacher, Khen Rinpoche, Lobsang
Gyaltsen Tarchin,
uh
Sorry.
I I got him to uh tell me the story
about Pabongka, okay?
And it was hard because uh he didn't
like to
answer my questions.
But I offered to drive him to Washington
every month,
which is a 5-hour drive,
and he couldn't get out of the car.
So, he told me the whole story, okay?
So, it's in uh
By the way, uh his nephew, uh which is
Geshe Lobsang Tarchin,
uh
was brought up by Khen Rinpoche as a
from childhood and uh became his uh main
attendant.
And he became the Gergan, Khentsen
Gergan.
What's that mean?
He became the house mom.
The babysitter for all the monks in our
college. There are 12 colleges in
Sera Mey according to the ancient
constitution of Sera Mey, which we found
in Russia,
the only copy. We found it in St.
Petersburg.
And uh
there are 12 houses, 12 colleges inside
of Sera
Sera Mey. Sera
monastery is divided into two halves,
Sera J, where they're not so educated,
and Sera Mey, which is vastly superior.
And uh there's a heavy rivalry between
the two halves, and there's a green line
in the monastery.
There's an invisible line, and you don't
cross it,
or something might happen,
okay?
It's tough stuff happens in the
monastery. You have no idea,
okay? But you don't go over that line.
So,
uh Uh, we're from Sera Mey, okay?
And we don't like Sera Jey, okay?
And there's lots of nice teachers at
Sera Jey, but don't tell anybody.
Okay. So, anyway, Sera Mey has 12
colleges. You're from Gerong College,
okay? You are affiliated as my student.
You are affiliated with Gerong College.
So,
in the structure of Sera of all the
great Tsongkhapa monasteries,
uh,
there are
what do you call them? Local houses.
Meaning, when I went to Princeton,
we had a Arizona club.
And all the students from Arizona,
we used to drink beer together, stuff
like that, okay? And, uh,
so, in the monastery, there are, uh,
local houses.
And Gerong is East East East Tibet.
Kham Amdo Mucci. Kham Amdo Kham Mucci
Mucci Kham Mucci Kham Mucci Kham Mucci
Kham Mucci Kham Mucci Kham Mucci Kham
Mucci Kham Mucci Kham Mucci.
Their language is totally weird, okay?
And,
not quite Tibetan, okay?
Uh, so, anyway, for some reason, my
teacher
was put into Gerong House by his uncle
or something at the age of
seven or five.
Okay? And, uh,
the highest lama in history from our
college is Pabongka.
He's Gerong House.
Got it?
He's from your college. So, you got to
be loyal.
Okay? He's from our college, okay? Got
it?
Which is a great honor, okay? Uh, to be
from his house, and, uh,
and and I had the honor of debating with
the third one, okay? The third Pabongka.
He was
doing his Geshe the year before I did my
Geshe, and he's from our college.
Tradition in the house
is, uh, you have to defend yourself
Geshe examination in your house before
you defend yourself in the monastery,
before you defend defend yourself in
Sera.
So, he had to defend
himself in our college, and we only had
50 monks there.
Uh
but the person who attacks him first
is the uh senior student who's not a
Geshe yet,
which was me.
So, uh I was supposed to attack him
first.
So, I'm attacking Pabongka
uh in the debates, and that was my job.
Guess what question I asked him.
Uh
after you get enlightened
and you become a Buddha,
how can you help suffering beings
cuz you don't have the karma
to see people suffering anymore.
You see them as high-level bodhisattvas.
All beings
uh become high-level bodhisattvas in
your heaven.
So, how can those people help suffering
beings
after they become a Buddha?
It's they all became humans instead of
dogs, you see?
So, there's no two toys
Got it?
in the universe for them.
So, we started like that.
And I was really getting them.
But when the opponent is a high Rinpoche
and you're just a schmuck,
uh the debate master will call off the
debate. He'll say "Olaso."
Which means
"Okay, next."
And I was like, "I got him. I got him."
He says, "Olaso."
You know, I'm like, "Dang." And then we
went uh on the porch and continued the
debate
uh for 3-4 hours, and uh it was cool.
And the abbot of uh the Tanta College
was with us.
And we we
uh
Okay.
O la sa
All right, anyway, that's Pabongka
Rinpoche. He has a nickname in the
secret teachings, in the Diamond Way
teachings. We don't call him Pabongka
Rinpoche. We call him Dechen Nyingpo.
Say Dechen.
Nyingpo. Dechen means the bliss
that's associated with seeing emptiness
in tantra.
Okay, great bliss. And Nyingpo means the
shin shin jing shin heart heart.
Just heart. Okay, heart of bliss. Okay.
So, that's his secret name.
But sometimes you'll hear him called
Dechen Nyingpo, okay?
He was the greatest teacher of his time.
Uh he graduated from my monastery, our
monastery, Sera Mey, from Gerong House.
Uh but he was not a high Geshe. He was
not a number one Geshe. He was like a
number three level Geshe, which is what
I am.
If you want to be a number two level,
you have to wait another four years. If
you want to be another one level, it
might take 10 more years. And I'm too
old.
And I probably couldn't do it anyway.
So,
it's much more examinations, okay? But
it's interesting, but he was also a
third level
Geshe. He was not a high level Geshe.
And uh
but he did something strange,
which is that he started teaching normal
people.
Uh and it was very very unusual. And I
And then 10 normal people, not monks,
came to his class, then 20 came to his
class, then 30 came to his class. By the
time he taught the Lamrim you're
studying in the morning, there were
1,000 people in the room. Okay?
And he became famous for teaching normal
people. He was the DCI of his time
and the ACI of his time. You see? And he
got heavily criticized. Very, very
heavily criticized.
And it was a very serious thing. Like
you could be murdered in those days.
And
he he stuck it out. You know, you're
going to see two photos of him.
One is
young, handsome
guy. Okay? Then 5 years later, he looks
terrible. He looks like somebody
beat him up, you know? And they say he
was attacked by
spirits.
He had a war with spirits. He had like a
1-year war
with a bunch of spirits, and it cost him
physically. He he he never recovered
physically. Okay? You can see the two
photos. It's very interesting.
Uh
so that's the story.
So he used to come to monasteries and
teach the Lamrim, which is what you're
studying in the morning.
Maybe for a month, okay?
And that's by the way how a Geshe gets
the Lamrim teachings.
You get them because a Lama visits
and teaches them extracurricular.
It's not part of the program.
It's a dessert.
Okay? So they'll they will cancel all
the classes for a month.
And some high, high Lama will come, like
Pabongka Rinpoche.
And he will teach the Lamrim for a
month. And then they'll invite all the
local people to come.
And that's what's happening in the
morning. That's what you're hearing in
the morning. Okay?
So
then there's a Nyepa. Say Nyepa.
Nyepa means the refreshment person.
Okay?
And you're Okay.
A monastery kitchen, like at Sera Mey.
We have to go serve in the kitchen.
Every 2 weeks we have to spend 2 days
there. Something like that.
When you wash the teapot, you need a
ladder
to get up to the top. And then you need
another ladder to get in.
And then you clean it like this. It's
It's tea for 3,000 people.
Okay? And uh
So, that's the nyerpa. The nyerpa runs
the
tea
at the lamrim teaching, which has a
thousand people. Everyone's got to get
tea. Everyone's got to get tsampa
porridge, okay?
So, my teacher, and by the way, usually
only pick the lazy monks. You don't pick
the geshes candidates
cuz they're too busy, okay? So, they
have a mixel. Mixel means uh
they don't have to do the dirty work in
the monastery. They can just study all
day. They're pampered.
The good geshe candidates are
you don't bother them. They don't have
to work like other people, okay?
My Lama was a goofball.
Okay? Goofball means uh bad boy. Never
studied.
Just played tricks on people. His
favorite trick, you know thumbtack? Like
small nails.
So, people in Tibet, inside the
monastery, they don't wear shoes.
Understand?
He would spread thumbtacks all over just
for fun. Then he'd watch them.
You know? And he was really naughty. He
was really bad. Uh
pak da say pak da.
Pak means little uh piece of uh
flour.
Like you make flour, and then you make
little balls like that.
And then when you're in the
prayer
3,000 guys
they're all going
You know, when they go
and then you go
You know, like 10 ft away, 3 m.
I pak da.
And
he was the best.
My teacher was number one.
And uh
he didn't study, he didn't do anything.
So, that's why he got stuck with Nyima.
He had to make refreshments.
And uh
he was doing it
and and Pabongka visited the kitchen
to check on the refreshments for the
teaching.
And he saw my teacher and he walked over
to him and he uh
puts his hands on his head
and he says, "This one is special.
This one is special."
Then he Then he just turned around and
left, you know.
Yeah.
And then something weird happened to my
teacher and he be
he he freaked out.
He got some kind of I don't know what,
spirit from Pabongka.
And he changed totally and uh
he was offered a very important
position, very good money,
big temple, you know, rest of your life
you drink tea and eat offerings.
And uh
he said, "No."
He told his teacher, "No, I'm not
going."
He said, "You're a fool, you know, the
rest of your life you're going to be
wealthy.
It's a good gig,
you know?"
And he said, "No,
I want to be a geshe." He said, "You, a
geshe?" And then my teacher said, "I'm
going to be a number one geshe, okay?"
And he's like, "Number one geshe?
Yeah, yeah, right. When you become a
number one geshe, I become the throne
holder of Tsongkhapa, you know?"
And my teacher got pissed off and he
worked really hard
and he became a number one geshe. And
then in his year
they had a competition of all the number
one geshes and he beat all of them.
So, we call Angi Dumbo. He was number
one
of I don't know 20,000 monks, okay?
Uh in the debates.
So, so try to win an argument with him.
You know, if he says the sky's not blue
he can prove it.
You know, don't even try to fight with
him.
Just go around him, understand? Okay.
Uh I still do that. Um
Okay.
Now, Pa Pa Bong means uh
boulder
and it's a special uh hermitage
retreat center
outside of uh Sera.
You you can walk to it. You have to hike
to it. It's like Diamond Mountain. It's
very similar to Diamond Mountain.
So, that retreat center was called Pa
Bong.
So, he was called
Pabongka.
But, he was not Pabongka. Okay? They
decided he would be the incarnation
of the abbot of Pabongka.
But, he wasn't. So, what's the story? Uh
He's actually recognized as the
reincarnation of Set Jangya.
Rope
Dorje.
Very, very famous lama of the emperor of
China.
And there's still a temple in Beijing
and I've seen it
uh dedicated to Jangya. Okay? So, this
is a very famous
teacher of the king of China, the
emperor of China, okay? And still the
the that uh temple is still there. I've
seen it. You can see it from the hotel
if you get to the 20th floor
cuz it's surrounded by other buildings,
you know? And uh
it's really cool, all right? Then um
he was very friendly with China and he
he he really got along with
with the Chinese. So,
in the year that Pabongka was born,
uh there was a lot of tension.
And people were afraid
to call him his real name, Tsenkhab
So, they called him Pabongka. Okay,
understand?
Uh they they named him a different name
because there was so much tension, uh
political tension, okay?
Anyway, that's who he really is, 1717 to
1786,
okay? Tsenkhab, this Tsenkhab, very very
famous. And he wrote four
volume Sedanta.
Mr. Word for $0.
Yeah, a study of all the schools. We
kind of did a Sedanta yesterday, okay?
But uh he was a he wrote the biggest and
the most famous, okay?
In his past life.
All right.
Uh now,
Pabongka Rinpoche had a special student,
okay?
Who wrote down his teachings.
Uh and uh these are the days before
iPhone recorders.
Okay?
Uh and
people were
taking notes like crazy.
And the the Lama just teaching, no
microphone, thousand people.
That you had to have a big voice, you
know? And uh so, his student was a high
Lama called Trijang Rinpoche. Say
Trijang.
Rinpoche. Born 1901.
Uh passed away 1981,
okay?
Uh
and Trijang Rinpoche became the highest
Geshe of his time and taught the Dalai
Lama, okay? He was the Dalai Lama's
teacher.
And he was amazing, kind
person, amazing scholar, amazing
teacher, and uh
why we have the
the gift of liberation, Why we have that
book is he
he spent 12 years editing those talks.
And I believe it's the greatest book
ever written in Tibetan. Okay?
It's the It's the
sweetest Tibetan language that ever was
written.
It's perfect. The book is totally
perfect. The Tibetan is exquisite. And
there
you know, nowadays because of the
Cultural Revolution, etc., the level of
Tibetan in Tibet is low.
It's I I called a monastery
many years ago to find a book. No one
could speak Tibetan.
Okay? So,
uh I believe that's going to be the
greatest book ever written
in Tibetan. And it was edited by Trijang
Rinpoche. Trijang Rinpoche was my
teacher's root lama. Okay? So, you're
Trijang Rinpoche's grand
great grand grandkids. Okay? Got it?
It's a good lineage.
Good lineage.
Okay.
Uh
So, the person who wrote the
introduction to your course and it's on
your homework is Khen Rinpoche
Geshe Lobsang Tarchin, my teacher. Okay?
Uh born 1921, passed away 2004. Okay?
All right. And he taught me for free
uh for 30 years.
And I lived with him uh for 25 years.
Okay?
And uh it was hard. He was hard person.
You could never win an argument.
He never once told me I did something
right.
When I finished my Geshe, first
foreigner in 600 years, he's
he's like, "Huh."
Uh but uh
So, uh
his nephew was his closest disciple. And
I'm pleased to say he's going to visit
this week.
Uh okay, he's very old now. He's about
80.
And we put him on a plane he agreed to
come.
And I asked him to give a teaching about
Khenpo Rinpoche, which is your
grandfather, okay?
Uh and just to tell us about his
personal life, you know, like tell us
some nice stories. Geshe
Lothar is his name. Uh
he's not a high Geshe. He's not a great
scholar. Uh
but he's a great storyteller. He's like
the best I know.
And he did become the debate master of
Sera Mey, okay? Uh which is kind of like
uh assistant abbot. It's vice abbot,
okay?
Uh so he did reach this position and uh
and he he helped me survive in the
monastery, okay? Without him I wouldn't
have survived. I was the only foreigner
to survive
in Sera Mey. It's still
in 600 years. And it's only because he
was so
he he said you need say the green line's
there, don't cross it. Don't don't walk
around there. I'm like, I don't see
anything. He's like, trust me.
You know, and
my whole career in the monastery is due
to him.
He taught me to tie my robes, you know,
everything. Dressed me up for the Geshe
exams. It's like getting married.
No, it's like three layers of
stupid historical stuff.
And uh
so you should be grateful to him.
Uh you should make him some nice
offerings, okay?
Red envelopes.
And
uh you should respect him, okay? Without
him I wouldn't be here, okay?
And he taught me to speak Tibetan cuz he
never stops talking.
Which is probably good luck for me,
okay?
And we lived together for about 10
years. So
he's good.
So you're going to get a nice uh
And I I don't think he'll be able to
come again. So, I think it's kind of
a special chance, okay?
What day is that, Tim?
Sat-
Yeah, he'll be staying here, but but
he'll give a lecture on Saturday
morning. Okay, so anyone's welcome to
come, okay?
Uh
now,
the text doesn't jump right into the
three principal paths.
Uh it starts with some preliminary
material, which is traditional, okay?
One of them,
perhaps the most traditional thing to
say first
is as you listen to this teaching,
avoid the three problems of the pot,
okay? Which we covered in
Kamala Shila. So, there as as long ago
as the Tang Dynasty, Tang Chao,
1700s?
700s.
Sh- Xuanzang.
1,300 years ago.
Uh as as early as that, they were
talking about this idea called the three
problems of the pot, okay? For $0.
Okay, $1.
Give me any of them. Give me one each.
Raise your hand, give me one. Uh don't
yell.
Okay, hustle.
Uh yeah, okay, somebody else.
You do that in the Geshe debates, you're
in trouble.
Huh?
Yeah, don't don't
You can't pour water into a dirty cup,
okay? So, what's it mean?
Let's do the other two. Yeah, give me
another one.
Huh?
Yeah, don't be like a
a a cup with hole in the bottom, okay?
The teacher teaches and teaches and
teaches and it leaks out. And I ask you
a question next day and you're like,
"Huh?"
W- What was yours?
Did you have another one?
Yeah, upside down. Like the teacher
tries to pour in the stuff, but you're
already full with with other ideas, you
know? You went to some
shaman ayahuasca ceremony and
you know, you're not open to these idea
these three ideas, okay? You're already
you're off on some strange thing, okay?
I had a student
from Ireland
who who she she actually translated the
mandala offering into
Gaelic.
Uh what do you call it? Celtic.
And uh it was amazing. And uh
then uh she was a very good student here
and then she uh
she went to a ayahuasca ceremony.
And she said, "I'm going to record it."
She turned on her video. They overdosed
her. She died on the video. You can
watch it, okay?
And uh
Okay, stupid idea. Got it?
Don't fill yourself up with
dumb
spiritual, you know, okay? Got it? You
can talk to her father.
Uh who's the head of the Ireland group,
okay?
Sad, very sad, okay?
So, anyway, don't be like a pot a a pot
The three things you should go into the
teaching before the teaching starts,
okay? Be open, okay? I'm going to learn
something new. I'll I'll open. It's not
what I'm used to,
but I'm open to it. Uh
It's like the
yoga class we had this morning. Yeah,
the teacher said, first thing he said,
"Look, I'm going to do stuff you didn't
do before. Just be open." Okay, that's
the first
part. Be open to it. Yeah, second one is
don't don't mix it up with other stuff.
And as an ACI teacher,
if you mix it up with other stuff, I'll
kick you out in 5 minutes, okay? Ready?
You mention ayahuasca in an ACI course,
and I will kick you out.
Clear?
Do I have to say it again?
Okay, you're teaching ACI.
All right? Now,
does that mean you can't teach something
else next week? No.
I'm not like that, okay? I understand
everyone in the room comes from a
different tradition, you know, maybe
you're from a
Jewish tradition, maybe you're from a
Christian tradition, maybe you're from a
Muslim tradition.
And maybe you're going to be teaching in
a Muslim country.
Uh then say cool stuff about Muslim,
okay? That's fine.
But don't do it in the middle of the
course. Don't mix it with this course,
okay? This course is ACI. This course is
Sun Kappa.
It's a formula for enlightenment.
If you add ayahuasca, it won't work
anymore.
People will fail. People will suffer for
more billions of years. Got it? Okay, so
I request I don't request, I order.
Don't mix other stuff with ACI. It
doesn't mean you can't teach other
stuff. You want to teach something else,
do it next week. Don't do it in the
middle of the ACI class, okay?
Understand? I request No, I order.
And I will remove your certification if
I find out you're mixing it with other
stuff, okay?
It's a formula, it works. I can tell you
it works. It happened to me. Stuff
happened to me
that is extraordinary, unbelievable.
So no one in the world can talk me out
of it. People have tried.
And I just laugh, you know, I'm like
What are you talking about?
You follow this correctly, you can see
the whole universe
in your meditation. You can meet every
living creature, billions.
You know, don't tell me ayahuasca.
Okay, I'm not interested. Then they're
like, "Yeah, but guess what?" I'm like,
"Yeah, but get out."
I'm not interested.
You know?
I already have a Model X.
Don't try to sell me a Volkswagen bug.
Okay?
And I'm not What do you call
sectarian?
I I tried it. It worked.
I got what I wanted. Okay? And And I say
you can do it, too.
But not if you mix it up. You're going
to ruin the
recipe. Okay?
Understand?
Okay.
And it's not cuz other traditions are
bad. It's not the point, you know? You
don't put mapo tofu recipe with a
chocolate cake recipe.
Right? If one is spicy, one is It's not
going to work out. It's going to be the
worst thing anyone ever made. Okay?
Mapo tofu is nice. Chocolate cake is
nice.
Don't mix them.
It's going to Let's do one one day and
serve it to everybody.
Wouldn't that be fun? Luca.
No? Let's serve it tomorrow in class so
people remember what I said.
You're all going to throw up.
Okay, mapo tofu chocolate cake.
Okay, maybe I'll make it just just so
you remember.
You'll tell your students
Yeah, your grandfather Lama Geshe
Michael, back in the old days, he made
us eat a chocolate mapo cake.
And it was terrible. So, please don't
mix up the teaching.
Okay?
Who's going to make a candy? You want to
make it?
Come on.
You guys are
I better teach Lama
obeying your Lama here. Um
Okay.
Uh
All Lamrim texts have three great
divisions. All Lamrim texts have three
great divisions. The teachings
A to Z, 1 2 3, step 4, 1 2 3 4 5
to how to get to Buddha-hood have three
big divisions, okay?
Uh and they depend on the motivation of
the person in the class, okay?
So, we call Kedu Chung. Say Kedu Chung.
Kedu Ding.
Kedu Chembo, okay? They're called little
people,
middle people, and big people, okay? The
Literally,
the word is little people,
medium people,
and big people, okay? Now,
it's just a difference of motivation.
Who's going to tell me little people's
motivation?
It doesn't refer to your heart height.
It refers to your heart.
Huh?
If that one is says
Yeah, I don't want to go to the lower
birth, okay? I don't want to go to the
lower birth, all right? I don't want to
be reborn as an animal in the hell or as
a spirit, okay? I don't want to go to
the lower birth.
That's little people's motivation.
For a hundred
300?
I'm spending too fast, right, shopping?
I'd make it a thousand.
Okay, thousand bucks.
But I'll pay you later.
Seriously.
What's the one teaching
that would satisfy
a small person?
What they want.
You owe me a thousand. You owe me a
thousand.
I'm ahead already.
Sheesh.
Good. Canceled.
Uh the pen. Okay, the pen.
All right, a person
who understands the pen teaching
correctly
cannot go to a lower birth. It's not
possible.
Okay? It you you destroy
all the seeds in your being
that would send you to a lower birth.
And can you imagine people complain that
I teach it too much?
They're going to thank me later.
Okay? If you understand the pen
correctly, Dorje Lama
is the technical term.
The mastery level of the path of
preparation,
which is when you have a deep
understanding of the pen.
Uh and the holder of the pen, by the
way.
Uh you cannot go to the lower realms.
It's not physically possible. Okay?
Cool? So, forget llama forget little
person. You already You already passed
that. Okay? What's medium person?
Yeah, I don't want any kind of samsara.
I don't want any kind of suffering life.
Okay? I don't care
if I become president
or I become a garbage man.
It all sucks. I don't want any of them.
Okay? I want to be
I want nirvana. Okay? For
me.
Okay? Then that's a hint about the big
person.
Big person wants
Yeah. Yeah, they want to everyone to be
enlightened, okay? Bodhicitta.
Bodhicitta. So, these are the three
great divisions
of the Lamrim teachings, okay?
All right, here we go.
Question nine, I'm making it. I got 3
minutes, Tim. I'm going to do it.
Uh
question nine, name the three principal
paths.
Okay, they are called renunciation,
which is a big English word
that nobody uses. It doesn't pass the
waiter test.
What's the waiter test, shopping mall?
Good.
When we decide in our translation team
whether to use a word or not,
I send
Allison to the Mexican restaurant
and I say, "Say to the waiter, what does
renunciation Say to the waiter, I'm
Chinese. Look, I don't know English very
well.
What's renunciation mean?"
If the waiter can't answer you, don't
use it in your translation.
But I did cuz that was 27 years ago.
Okay, and that's what I was taught, all
right? And it's not a great translation,
okay? It's not a great translation.
Renunciation Okay, now follow me, okay?
Now we're going to do content.
Renunciation means I will not ride in a
fancy car.
I will not have a lot of money. I will
eat only dal and rice,
you know, and bananas. Uh I will live
simply.
I will not dress nice clothes, you know?
This is the classical
meaning
of renunciation, okay?
And it's not
what we want.
It's not what we want you to do, okay?
It's not We talked about it yesterday,
okay? If you practice Buddhism properly,
you will be successful whether you want
to be or not.
And you can run,
but the money will follow you. I'm
sorry.
Okay? And fame and clothes and
cars and
they will chase you down the street.
You can't avoid them, okay? If you plant
If you understand seeds
and you plant seeds only to serve other
people,
you will still be super successful. I'm
sorry, okay? How many
of the great saints of Buddhism were
princes?
Aśvaghoṣa, Asaṅga,
Siddhartha,
okay? Atiśa, okay? Come on, okay? Got
it? So, it doesn't mean
you have to run away from money and cars
and
girlfriends.
Okay? It doesn't mean that, okay? It
doesn't mean that.
It means
recognize
that if you don't figure out the seed
system,
everything around you is going to
collapse and die, including you.
Okay? If you don't figure out
how to plant more seeds than you use up,
you will die.
And you will not have money, and you
will not have a partner, and you will
not have happiness, okay?
Uh it doesn't mean you shouldn't have a
partner or money or happiness. It
doesn't mean that, okay? Got it?
That's not renunciation, okay?
I tried to go to a cave. I did go to a
cave. I spent uh
I don't know, a month in a cave.
It's not a good place.
There's bugs. I had a rattle I had a
highly deadly rattlesnake green
rattlesnake.
Bite you once, you're dead. There's no
cure.
Uh I had a wolf come in.
I had spiders crawling over me all day.
It's not cool, okay? That's not
renunciation.
Get a place with a door.
Okay? Get it If you can find a cave with
a door.
Okay? But I thought somehow a cave would
be more holy or something.
It's not. It's just irritating, okay?
Got it?
Have a nice
I like to say I like a small house,
but I want it elegant.
Okay? Why?
I hate cleaning.
I don't want cleaning. I don't want a
house with five rooms in it.
If you are Somebody offered me one
recently.
You know his name.
And I said, "No, I don't want it." He
keeps asking me. I said, "I built it for
you." I said, "I don't want it."
You know, I don't want a house that I
have to clean all day, you know? I want
a small house, el- you know, sweet,
cool, elegant,
tasteful,
like
but small.
Less cleaning, okay? So, that's
renunciation. Got it?
Uh you can have a nice house. It's It's
fine, okay? Got it?
It's not renunciation to wear bad
clothes
and to not have a job
and to wander around and stay on other
piece of people's couches and
I don't let those yogis in my house.
Why?
They always leave the refrigerator
empty,
these holy people.
Okay? They always park on your couch.
You go to work to pay for the couch,
and then uh
your refrigerator's empty when you come
home.
I don't want it to be like that, okay?
That's not an ACI teacher. That's not a
yogi. That's a bum.
Okay? That's a Dharma bum, okay?
Make your own money, be responsible.
That's a Dharma teacher.
The best You know, I made a list of the
best ACI teachers I know.
And they're all responsible people.
Some of them have families. Some of them
have
high jobs, you know, own own big
companies.
Uh
but they're responsible. Got it?
I would say that's one of the most
important qualities of a I'm not going
to trust you with my life
if you can't feed yourself.
You see what I mean? I'm not going to
trust you with my spiritual life
if you can't figure out how to make $50
a day.
Understand? Got it?
Okay. All right. Second one.
Uh okay, so first principal path, call
it renunciation cuz I don't want to
change all the masters.
Uh but what it means is
I'm tired of seeing the suffering of the
world. I'm tired.
I'm tired of it, okay? I'm tired of it.
That's all. That's all. I can't take it
anymore.
Okay? These wars in Syria, in you know,
Israel.
Uh Oritsa, France got a missile dropped
on them few days ago.
You know,
uh I'm tired of seeing this stuff.
You know, I'm tired of these crazy
things going on. I'm tired of people
dying
all around me, you know?
I I it makes me I'm tired.
Okay, that's that's the first principal
path, okay? What do you got to write in
the homework?
I'm tired.
I'm I that's all I can take. I don't
want it anymore, okay? I don't want to
people dying around me.
Okay? It's so lonely. My my old lady,
her worst suffering is that she's the
last one.
There's no one she can call. They all
died.
Okay? And it will happen to us. It will
happen to you. Okay?
There will be a day when the the last
person from this teen training dies.
Okay? So, I'm tired. I I don't want to
see this anymore. I want to fix it.
Okay? That's the first principal path.
Got it?
I'm tired.
If you want to show off your English,
put renunciation.
But, I'm happy to take I'm tired on the
homework.
I'm tired of this stuff. You know, let's
fix it. Let's get it. Let's Let's stop
this.
There are planets
where they stopped it. Okay?
There's whole planets where people
studied ACI.
And no one dies anymore.
And no one has to meet irritating people
anymore.
Okay? Everyone has a Model X
until Model Z comes out.
Okay? Everyone's
happy cuz they understand Buddhism. And
every planet goes through this
evolution.
Some are already finished. Some are
halfway through like us.
And some didn't get Buddhism yet. Okay?
I'm I'm tired of it. Okay? That's the
first one. First principal path. Second
principal path
is called bodhicitta. Okay?
If you see a book that says the Buddha
mind
as a translation of bodhicitta, throw it
out.
Okay? They don't know what they're
talking about. You know, people always
give me books at the airport. Oh, here
Geshe, here's a book. You know, I'm
like, oh, thanks.
I go through customs and I throw it out
on the other side.
Uh
especially if it says body mind
or enlightenment mind. Come on.
Okay? It means, you ready?
The wish to become enlightened. It It
doesn't mean an enlightened mind. That's
already enlightened. Duh.
Got it? Okay.
You have it before you become a Buddha.
Mainly.
Okay. I want to become enlightened
so I can split my body into a billion
pieces
and help all the people who are
suffering of things that I'm tired of.
Got it? It's natural
next step. Okay? I'm fed up with seeing
people die.
Then well, what are you going to do
about it? Huh. I'm going to become
Buddha cuz then I can split my body and
teach ACI in a billion planets instead
of just one country on the internet. Got
it?
Okay?
That's That's all. I call it the wish
for enlightenment and I
capitalize the
W. Okay?
I'm fed up with bodhicitta. Citta does
mean mind. Bodhi does mean Buddhahood.
Bodhicitta doesn't mean enlightened
mind. It's a bad tran- super bad
translation.
That's a James Bond song.
Super bad.
It's super bad. Okay, got it?
It doesn't mean that at all. If you see
that in a translation, just It means the
rest of book is bad also. Okay?
If they didn't figure that much out.
Okay, got it?
Pet peeve.
Uh
bad translations are 90% of my
irritation. Uh word is the other 10%.
Just kidding.
Okay. Third principle path.
If you want to become a Buddha
to help all living beings, you got to
see emptiness directly. That's all.
Third principle path. Call it wisdom.
But you know, in English wisdom means
like wise person. They don't drive too
fast. They don't eat
stuff with a a of cholesterol in it.
That's not wisdom. We're not talking
about that. We're talking about Have you
seen emptiness directly? Okay?
You can be a person like that.
If If you follow this class,
if you follow these teachings, if you do
the meditations you learn here, you can
become an Arya. You can join the Gardena
Asanga Tsongkhapa. You have everything
you need. Everyone in this room has
access to the direct perception of
emptiness. And most of the people
outside this room don't.
Okay? Honestly, frankly, okay?
You have everything you need
to see emptiness directly. If you see
it,
in the same hour,
you see every planet
and every person on every planet, and
you love them intensely
during that hour. Got it?
Then what else is going to bother you
your whole life?
How can anyone make you upset or
irritated?
You know, they're like,
"I don't like what you cooked for
dinner." Hey, man, I saw all the billion
planets, okay?
Calm down.
I don't care what you think about my
dinner, okay? Got it? You can't irritate
an Arya almost.
Unless you have bad translations.
Uh
but uh
Okay? I mean, what's there to talk about
if you saw your own Buddha-hood?
Okay? In the future. You saw the day,
and you know it's coming.
And then who's going to irritate you? I
mean, it's uh Andreas teaches a really
heavy yoga class, maybe.
But come on. I Isn't that worth it?
Just to do the ACI, see emptiness, so
nobody can irritate you? That's worth
it, right?
That's worth coming here a bunch of
times.
Okay? So, you can do it, okay? And that
experience
that happens right after you see
emptiness directly, in the same hour.
Uh there's nothing like it, okay? What
happens the hour before you see
emptiness directly?
Come on.
Give me some specifics.
You see a seed opening in your own mind
for the first time.
In in mind-only language, you catch the
storehouse opening.
You
you see, and it always happens like
that.
Okay? Technically, Dorje Lopon Tenzin
just before you an an hour before you
see emptiness directly,
for the first time,
you see that this laptop is coming out
of your seeds.
Coming from you, okay? Everything. Then
who's going to piss you off after that?
You know, your husband who yells at you?
He's also coming from you. If you want
to punch somebody, punch yourself.
Okay? Got it? Okay? Understand?
So, all these things happen. You confirm
dependent origination 1 hour before you
see emptiness directly.
Because dependent origination just means
stuff is coming out of seeds in your
mind, okay? And you see it directly.
Why can't you see it before that?
Geshe Michael has been teaching you year
after year. Why didn't you see it?
It's too fast. It's 65 a second.
You got to meditate, okay? You got to
have good meditation, okay? Got it?
Good seeds. All right. Those are the
three principal paths. Let's review.
Number one,
I'm tired. God bless. I'm tired.
Okay? Number two,
I want to be a Buddha
to help the universe.
I'm headed for the stars next week.
I'm finishing this planet this week. I
got it wrapped up by Sunday.
And then I'm headed out. Okay, that's
intention. Okay, though you can say the
wish, capital W, I'll take it on a
homework, okay?
What's By the way, I finished the
homework, Tim, and took me
the master.
It's like six pages, good luck. I didn't
write the homework for tonight. But I'll
do it
by morning, okay?
Uh
third one?
Direct perception
Yeah, the the they call it DPE. I I I
didn't invent that. It's not so bad.
Somebody changed their car license to
DPE.
Direct perception emptiness, okay?
All right. Okay, got it? Those are
what
ACI course one
is all about. That's the only
main subject of ACI course one, okay?
So
all of Buddhism is covered in ACI course
one.
Why did you do the rest of the courses,
Geshe la?
I don't know, it's just fun.
Okay, um
the last homework question.
I'm not giving you a break, okay? You
got to pee pee, just get up and go,
okay? You're allowed.
Yes, but it's got to be really good cuz
otherwise I won't finish the class.
Okay, it's not good. All right.
Uh
The last question is, are these three
principal paths physical, mental, or are
they concepts?
Mental. They are attitudes. They are
attitudes, okay? They're not paths.
They're not uh concrete.
Okay?
Uh they're not even instructions.
They're not sutras.
They're ideas. They're ways of thinking,
attitudes, okay? Should have been called
the three principal attitudes.
Okay. All right, I finished homework
one. Let me finish the You sure?
Okay, there's no microphone. I'm sorry.
Oh, okay.
Three problems of the path. Number one,
you're not open to learning. You're
You're upside down.
Number two,
what you hear, you mix it up with other,
you know, ayahuasca shaman stuff.
Number three, are you leaky?
Geshe la teaches you something tonight,
you forgot it by tomorrow.
Got it? You don't hold it. You don't
retain it. Okay.
All right, we're going to the second
homework. You guys okay?